# XIAOJIAN XU

[Homepage] [Google Scholar] [Github] [Twitter] [Linkedin]

Department of Computer Science and Engineering & Washington University in St. Louis

### ABOUT ME

#### Current research

My current research pursues to combine computational imaging, optimization, and machine learning to
enable new intelligent imaging technology for various imaging applications including denoising, deblurring,
super-resolution, image segmentation, optical microscopy, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), radar, and autonomous driving, etc. My research efforts are taking place at two complementary levels: (a) the fundamental
and mathematical aspects of imaging; (b) application-oriented projects in collaboration with researchers in
medicine, biology, and computer vision.

### Research interests

· Computational Imaging, Optimization, Deep Learning, Inverse Problems, Computer Vision, Image Processing

# EDUCATION

Washington University in St. Louis (WUSTL), St. Louis, MO, USA

9/2017-6/2022 (expected)

Ph.D student in Computer Science (GPA: 3.87/4.00), advised by Dr. Ulugbek Kamilov

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China (UESTC), Chengdu, China 9/2014-6/2017

M.Eng in Communication & Information Engineering (Graduated with Honors)

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China (UESTC), Chengdu, China 9/2010-6/2014

• B.Eng in Communication Engineering (GPA: 3.89/4.00)

# Work Experience

#### Facebook Reality Labs Research (FRLR)

5/2021-8/2021

Research intern with Dr. Brian Wheelwright

Seattle (remote)

- Simulated the end-to-end peripheral display system (lens-lets and display LED array included) in Oculus and implemented a corresponding efficient ray-tracing model for the system, all from scratch.
- Solved the display calibration problem with the simulated display system and ray tracing model by designing various optimization strategies.
- Designed a novel deep-learning-based (neural representation) method for the challenging pupil-movement-based camera-to-display mapping in the virtual reality (VR) system, which achieved real-time rendering capability (0.3 sec) without losing visual quality.

### Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories (MERL)

5/2019-8/2019

Research intern with Dr. Hassan Mansour

Boston

- Investigated in 3D tomographic imaging problems challenged by noise corruption, data acquisition and problem model establishment.
- Established the whole system for data acquisition, and solved the problem by proposing two distinct methods, model-based optimization and data driven deep learning.

#### Research Experience

#### Model-based deep learning for imaging and vision

8/2020 - Present

- Working on provable model-based unfolding networks for medical imaging application and computer vision tasks with various noise corruption (Gaussian, Poisson, etc) challenges.
- Developed imaging-model-assisted unsupervised, self-supervised and supervised learning methods for different imaging tasks such as denoising, deblurring, MRI, CT.

Learning-based optimization for imaging and vision

8/2020 - Present

- Conducted different image reconstruction tasks (e.g. debluring, super-resolution, Poisson/Gaussian denoising, compressive sensing, phase retrieval, MRI, CT, etc.) by combining the physical models together with the deep-learning priors.
- Extensively investigated in the variants of Plug-and-Play priors (PnP) and Regularized by denoising (RED) approaches for various imaging tasks (both theory and practice).
- Conducted the first mathematical analysis of plug-and-play priors (PnP) framework for minimum mean squared error (MMSE) denoisers. This result provides new insights into usage of deep-learning denoisers in PnP.
- Designed a practically efficient denoiser scaling technique that can greatly boost the performance of PnP algorithms under deep-learning priors by explicitly adjusting the amount of PnP regularization.
- Developed the stochastic variant of the PnP-ADMM algorithm for large-scale optimization and proved its convergence.

#### Compressed and stochastic algorithms for large-scale imaging

7/2018 - Present

- Developed the stochastic variant of iterative PnP and unfolding networks for large scale imaging applications with convergence guarantee.
- Developed compressed proximal algorithms for stochastic optimization problems and was the first to prove the convergence.

# Learning-based magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and quantitative-MRI (qMRI) 7/2018 - Present

- Developed both supervised and self-supervised deep-learning-based methods for motion artifact removal in qMRI mapping.
- Investigated the application of reinforcement learning, neural representation and sparse representation in fast MRI reconstruction.
- · Working on macroscopic-magnetic-field-inhomogeneities-corrected MRI image reconstruction

#### Some earlier research experience

3/2014 - 6/2017

- Intelligent home system design and development.
- Routing and resource scheduling algorithms for large-scale network software defined netwroks (SDN).

# LIST OF PUBLICATIONS

### **Preprints**

- [1] **X. Xu** et al., "Learning-based Motion Artifact Removal Networks (LEARN) for Quantitative  $R_2^*$  Mapping," arXiv:2109.01622 [eess], Sep. 2021, [Online]. Available: http://arxiv.org/abs/2109.01622
- [2] S. Kahali, S. V. V. N. Kothapalli, **X. Xu**, U. S. Kamilov, and D. A. Yablonskiy, "Deep-Learning-Based Accelerated and Noise-Suppressed Estimation (DANSE) of quantitative Gradient Recalled Echo (qGRE) MRI metrics associated with Human Brain Neuronal Structure and Hemodynamic Properties," bioRxiv, 2021, doi: 10.1101/2021.09.10.459810.

#### **Published**

(\* indicates equal contribution)

- [3] X. Xu, Y. Sun, J. Liu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Provable convergence of plug-and-play priors with MMSE denoisers," IEEE Signal Process. Lett., vol. 27, pp. 1280–1284, 2020.
- [4] X. Xu, J. Liu, Y. Sun, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Boosting the performance of plug-and-play priors via denoiser scaling," in 54th Asilomar Conf. on Signals, Systems, and Computers, 2020, pp. 1305–1312.
- [5] X. Xu\*, Y. Sun\*, Z. Wu\*, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Scalable Plug-and-Play ADMM With Convergence Guarantees," IEEE Trans. on Comp. Imag., vol. 7, pp. 849–863, 2021.
- [6] J. Liu, Y. Sun, W. Gan, X. Xu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "SGD-Net: Efficient Model-Based Deep Learning With Theoretical Guarantees," IEEE Trans. on Comp. Imag., vol. 7, pp. 598–610, 2021.
- [7] J. Liu, Y. Sun, W. Gan, X. Xu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Stochastic Deep Unfolding for Imaging Inverse Problems," in IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), 2021, pp. 1395–1399.

- [8] X. Xu, O. Dhifallah, H. Mansour, P. T. Boufounos, and P. V. Orlik, "Robust 3D Tomographic Imaging of the Ionospheric Electron Density," in 2020 IEEE Int. Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS), 2020, pp. 437–440.
- [9] J. Liu, Y. Sun, X. Xu, and U. S. Kamilov, "Image restoration using total variation regularized deep image prior," in 2019 IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), 2019, pp. 7715–7719.
- [10] X. Xu and U. S. Kamilov, "SignProx: One-bit proximal algorithm for nonconvex stochastic optimization," in IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), Brighton, UK, May 2019, pp. 7800–7804.

### INVITED TALKS

- SIAM Conference on Imaging Science, 07/2020
- UCLouvain, Image and Signal Processing Group Seminar, 09/2020
- Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems, and Computers, 10/2021

# REVIEWER EXPERIENCE

- Conferences: ISBI, ICASSP
- **Journals**: IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP), IEEE Transactions on Computational Imaging (TCI), Optics Communications

# TEACHING & SUPERVISION EXPERIENCE

#### (Head) TA for Optimization

2019-2020

Assistant Instructor

St. Louis

 Worked as an assistant instructor for course "Optimization" and "Large-Scale Optimization for Data Science" for four semesters. Developed and held weekly tutorial lectures and occasional guest lectures, hold office hours, answer questions online, design homework and exams.

#### Students supervision

7/2018-Present

Research Supervisor

St. Louis

#### **Current students**

- Eddie Chandler, "Inhomogeneity correction for MRI", now B.S. student at WUSTL
- Yixuan Luo, "Deep-learning-based image segmentation", now M.S. student at WUSTL
- Michael Kincheloe, "Reinforcement learning for MRI artifacts correction". now B.S. student at WUSTL Previous students
- Zhixin Sun, "Neural representation for MRI reconstruction", coming Ph.D student at WUSTL
- Weijie Gan, "Fast MRI reconstruction and artifacts correction", now Ph.D student at WUSTL
- Jiarui Xing, "Deep-learning-based MRI artifacts correction", now Ph.D student at University of Virginia
- Shiqi Xu, "Sparse Fourier ptychographic microscopy", now Ph.D student at Duke University
- Hao Tang, "Adversarially robust classifiers for image reconstruction", now M.S. student at WUSTL
- Ryogo Suzuki, "Unfolding networks for image restoration", now at Rakuten Group, Inc.
- Yukun Li, "Single image denoising", now at Baidu Inc.
- Fa Long, "Dictionary learning for image restoration", now at Tencent Inc.

# SKILLS

- Languages: Python, Matlab, C, Java
- Skills: Optimization, Inverse problems, Tensorflow, Pytorch, Deep learning, Linux, TCP/IP

### Awards & Honors

#### Honors

Honored Ph.D student in Computer Science & Engineering department (WUSTL)

2021

Outstanding Graduate Student (UESTC)

2017

### Scholarship

Graduate Student First-Rank Academic Scholarship	2016
Graduate Student Second-Rank Academic Scholarship	2015
Graduate Student First-Rank Academic Scholarship	2014
National Inspirational Scholarship	2013
People's First-Rank Scholarship	2012
National Inspirational Scholarship	2011
Others	
• Third-prize of 'Internet+' Entrepreneurship Competition in Sichuan Province	2016
Great Award of Intelligent City Technology Competition	2016
Award of Hackathon Programming Competition	2015
<ul> <li>Second Prize of Electronic Design Competition in UESTC</li> </ul>	2011